<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>SLA Theoretical Positions on Brandon JP Lambert</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/</link><description>Recent content in SLA Theoretical Positions on Brandon JP Lambert</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:13:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Collaborative Knowledge Construction</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/collaborative-knowledge-construction/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/collaborative-knowledge-construction/</guid><description>🤝 Learning Together Knowledge builds collaboratively through interaction rather than transmission from teacher to student. Collaborative dialogue serves as knowledge-building emphasizing co-construction.
Beyond Banking Education Freire&amp;rsquo;s critique of &amp;ldquo;banking&amp;rdquo; education applies to language learning:
Banking Model Problems Teachers deposit knowledge Students receive passively Information transfers unchanged Power remains unexamined Collaborative Alternative Knowledge emerges in dialogue All participants contribute Understanding transforms through interaction Power gets redistributed We learn together or not at all.</description></item><item><title>Institutional Awareness</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/institutional-awareness/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/institutional-awareness/</guid><description>🏫 Schools as Non-Neutral Spaces Educational institutions shape and constrain language learning in ways requiring explicit acknowledgment. Analysis at institutional levels reveals schools as non-neutral spaces.
The Hidden Curriculum Beyond explicit teaching, institutions teach through:
Spatial arrangements encoding hierarchies Temporal structures defining legitimate learning Assessment regimes determining value Linguistic policies privileging varieties Critical awareness demands analyzing these structures.
Institutional Power Structures Schools embody multiple power relations:
Administrative Hierarchies Who makes decisions?</description></item><item><title>Complex Dynamic Development</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/complex-dynamic-development/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/complex-dynamic-development/</guid><description>🔀 Non-Linear Trajectories Language acquisition follows non-linear trajectories influenced by multiple interacting factors. Complexity theory reveals variability as informative, not noise.
Beyond Linear Progress Traditional models assume steady upward progress. Complex dynamic systems theory (CDST) recognizes:
U-shaped development where performance temporarily declines Sudden jumps after apparent plateaus Variability as inherent not problematic Individual paths that diverge dramatically Learning is ecological, not mechanical.
Key Principles Interconnectedness Everything connects to everything:
Vocabulary affects grammar acquisition Motivation influences pronunciation Anxiety shapes comprehension Context determines performance Emergence Complex behaviors emerge from simple interactions:</description></item><item><title>Intercultural Communicative Competence</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/intercultural-communicative-competence/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:10:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/intercultural-communicative-competence/</guid><description>🌏 Beyond Linguistic Accuracy Language learning develops ability to navigate culturally diverse and socially complex perspectives. Evolution from competence to citizenship joins critical inter-ideological approaches and virtual reality applications.
From Competence to Citizenship The field has evolved through stages:
Communicative Competence Knowing grammar plus how to use it appropriately in context.
Intercultural Competence Adding cultural awareness and sensitivity to linguistic skills.
Intercultural Citizenship Acting in the world to address injustice and promote understanding.</description></item><item><title>Teacher Identity</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/teacher-identity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:09:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/teacher-identity/</guid><description>🎭 Examining Teacher Positioning Teachers must critically examine ideologies, identities, and positioning within classroom power structures. The framework now includes raciolinguistic ideologies and emotional-sensory dimensions.
Unexamined Identity Perpetuates Inequality Teacher identity isn&amp;rsquo;t neutral—it carries:
Linguistic ideologies about &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; language Cultural assumptions about learning styles Racial positioning affecting expectations Class backgrounds shaping perspectives Without examination, these reproduce inequalities.
Native Speaker Fallacy The native speaker teacher myth persists despite evidence:
Problems with Native-Speakerism Privileges accident of birth over expertise Ignores multilingual competencies Perpetuates racial hierarchies Devalues local teachers Alternative Frameworks Multilingual teacher as model Local teacher as cultural bridge Expert teacher regardless of L1 Collaborative teaching teams Raciolinguistic Ideologies Teachers must confront how race and language intersect:</description></item><item><title>Emergent Motivation</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/emergent-motivation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:08:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/emergent-motivation/</guid><description>💫 Motivation in Relationships Motivation emerges organically through systems of interrelations rather than as fixed individual trait. While traditional self-system models face validation critiques, directed motivational currents offer alternatives emphasizing prolonged engagement.
Beyond Individual Psychology Traditional motivation research treats it as residing in individuals. Emergent perspectives see motivation as:
Arising between people not within them Fluctuating dynamically not remaining stable Context-dependent not universal Socially constructed not individually possessed Motivation grows in relationships.</description></item><item><title>Language Socialization</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/language-socialization/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:07:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/language-socialization/</guid><description>🌍 Language as Cultural Practice Language acquisition includes linguistic forms plus pragmatic and cultural knowledge through social experience. The framework emphasizes transnational, multimodal, and multilingual processes beyond traditional contexts.
Beyond Grammar and Vocabulary Language socialization recognizes that competence requires:
Knowing when to speak or stay silent Understanding how to show respect or solidarity Recognizing what can and cannot be said Performing who you are through language Language without culture is just noise.</description></item><item><title>Communities of Practice</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/communities-of-practice/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:06:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/communities-of-practice/</guid><description>🏘️ From Periphery to Center Language learning means movement from peripheral to full participation in communities of practice. The framework extends to identity as a time/space concept and includes virtual reality communities.
Legitimate Peripheral Participation Lave and Wenger&amp;rsquo;s framework reconceptualizes learning as changing participation:
Starting at edges of communities Gradually moving inward through practice Earning membership through contribution Eventually becoming core members Language proficiency equals community membership.
Communities Not Classrooms Real language develops in real communities:</description></item><item><title>Mediation in Language Learning</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/mediation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:05:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/mediation/</guid><description>🔗 Learning Through Tools Language acquisition is mediated through social tools, psychological tools, and material artifacts. Mediation now includes technology-mediated dimensions: teacher-assigned, program interactions, and learner-initiated.
The Mediational Triangle Vygotskian theory positions all learning as mediated—never direct but always through tools:
Subject (learner) Object (language/goal) Mediating artifacts (tools/signs) Learning happens through tools, not despite them.
Types of Mediation Social Mediation Through collaboration with others:
Teacher scaffolding Peer interaction Community participation Family support Psychological Mediation Through mental tools:</description></item><item><title>Multi-Competence &amp; Translanguaging</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/multi-competence-translanguaging/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:04:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/multi-competence-translanguaging/</guid><description>🧠 The Multilingual Mind All languages in a learner&amp;rsquo;s repertoire are interconnected resources, not separate systems to be suppressed. Multi-competence joins translanguaging space theory and decolonizing pedagogical projects.
Beyond Monolingual Bias Traditional language teaching assumes monolingual native speakers as the goal. Multi-competence recognizes that multilingual minds work differently—and that&amp;rsquo;s an advantage:
Integrated systems not separate compartments Dynamic resources not fixed competencies Creative potential not deficient performance Unique capabilities not failed native speaker approximation The Translanguaging Space Li Wei&amp;rsquo;s translanguaging space describes where multilingual speakers:</description></item><item><title>Person-in-Context</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/person-in-context/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/person-in-context/</guid><description>👥 Whole Persons, Real Histories Learners and teachers must be understood as whole persons with histories, goals, and multiple identities—not just language users. The relational view now addresses deterritorialized and unbounded digital contexts.
Beyond the Language Learner Label Traditional SLA research often reduces people to &amp;ldquo;learners&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;non-native speakers.&amp;rdquo; The person-in-context view insists on recognizing:
Life histories shaping current learning Multiple identities beyond student role Future aspirations driving present choices Complex motivations beyond instrumental goals Real Persons Create Real Learning Authentic learning emerges when we acknowledge:</description></item><item><title>Transformational Identity</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/transformational-identity/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:02:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/transformational-identity/</guid><description>🔄 Languages Remake Us Language learning fundamentally transforms learner identity, motivation, and self-concept over time. The multilingual subject occupies a third space between languages while undergoing transformations in their entire approach to language use.
The Third Space Multilingual speakers don&amp;rsquo;t simply switch between separate identities—they inhabit a unique third space:
Between languages rather than in them Creating new meanings unavailable to monolinguals Navigating multiple cultural frameworks simultaneously Transforming continuously through linguistic encounters Identity as Process We don&amp;rsquo;t just learn languages; languages remake who we are through:</description></item><item><title>Dialogic Acquisition</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/dialogic-acquisition/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/dialogic-acquisition/</guid><description>🗣️ Language Through Dialogue Language emerges through social interaction and mediation, not individual cognitive processing alone. Modern sociocultural theory incorporates emotional experience showing emotion-cognition integration and digital mediation stages.
The Social Foundation Language is co-constructed through dialogue involving:
Social interaction as primary driver Private speech for self-regulation Artifacts as mediating resources Emotional and cognitive development as inseparable processes Beyond Input-Output Models Traditional acquisition models treat language as information to be processed.</description></item><item><title>Ecological Language Learning</title><link>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/ecological-language-learning/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://vocal-pony-24e3de.netlify.app/teaching-learning/sla-theory/ecological-language-learning/</guid><description>🌐 The Ecological Framework Language acquisition occurs through complex interactions between learners, contexts, and communities—not through isolated cognitive processes. The ecological framework extends from individual affordances to planetary scales, addressing how learners navigate power in multilingual contexts.
Core Principles Learning is inseparable from the ecological systems in which it occurs. This requires:
Analysis of trajectories across communities Movement between linguistic expectations Recognition of both institutional structures and digital affordances Beyond Individual Processing The ecological approach challenges traditional cognitivist models by positioning language learning as fundamentally interconnected with:</description></item></channel></rss>